Records of the Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Development Network
World Bank Group Archives
Records of the Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Development Network
1994 - 2003 (predominant 1998 - 2003)
WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_92
26.56 linear feet of textual records
World Bank Group Archives
Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Development Network
The Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Development Network (ESSD) was created in 1997 as part of President Wolfensohn's reorganization of the World Bank. The reorganization's objective was to strike a better balance between country focus and sectoral excellence. It was also motivated by recognition that the Bank's development programs were excessively driven by a culture of lending. The need to increase attention towards on client needs and the quality of results was addressed.
To facilitate sharingof expertise and knowledge, the Bank established networks that linked Bank-wide communities of staff working in the same field across organizational boundaries and with external partners. The networks were intended to link staff working in the same sectors throughout the Bank, whether the staff member was located in the regional Vice Presidencies, sectoral departments, Independent Evaluation Group (IEG, formerly the Operations Evaluation Group [OED]), World Bank Institute (WBI), or Development Economics (DEC). The objectives and responsibilities of the networks were many: reduce fragmentation; increase information flow; set priorities; manage quality; run the information system; consolidate external partnerships; vet staff promotions; and disseminate best practices. The work programs of network staff focused on:
* Global knowledge - putting the best development knowledge in the hands of Bank task teams; ensuring that the knowledge base was accessible to external clients; and contributing to the growth of the knowledge base.
* Enhanced skills - developing and providing content to training courses; establishing professional and technical standards for professional development.
* Shared strategies - assisting regional and central units to develop a common sector agenda, and ensuring that skills are effectively deployed across the entire network. Network leadership assumed responsibility for global programs, sector strategy development and evaluation, strategic partnerships, and learning and dissemination.
* Best teams and best practices - improving the Bank's flexibility and mobility by building stronger task teams and delivering higher quality products.
* Institutional initiatives - providing substantial support for new Bank-wide initiatives, such as social development, rural development, financial sector, anti-corruption, human resources, and knowledge partnerships.
ESSD was one of the first of three networks to be created in 1997; the others were the Poverty Reduction and Economic Management Network (PREM) and the Human Development Network (HDN). Soon after, in 1997-98, the Private Sector and Infrastructure Network (PSI) was created. In 2000-01, the Operation Policy and Strategy Department became the Operations Policy and Country Services Network (OPCS). In 2003-04, the PSI became the Financial and Private Sector Development Network (FPSD). In 2007 ESSD was combined with Infrastructure to form the Sustainable Development Network (SDN).
ESSD is organized in the same way as the other Bank networks. Each network is headed by a vice president and head of network. Under the vice president is a network council which that oversees the entire network. The council is composed of the top network managers from each Region and is responsible for setting the overall agenda for the network and for promoting effective deployment of skills across network units. It deliberates on issues relevant to the functions and objectives of the network - e.g., strategy; people; knowledge; quality/business process; and external partnerships.
Each thematic network covers several related sectors of development. When the ESSD was created in 1997, it contained three sector departments: Environment Department (ENV); Rural Development Department (RDV); and Social Development Department (SDV). It also contained the Secretariat of the Consultative Group for International Agricultural Research (CGIAR). In 2002, RDV was renamed the Agriculture and Rural Development Department (ARD). Each sector department has its own board, with representatives drawn from the Regions as well as from the network itself. The sector boards are accountable to the network council and are supported by a secretariat.
Published
The fonds consists of records that reflect the various activities of the Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Development Vice Presidencyof (ESSDVP) and its oversight of, and involvement with, sector departments within the network. Note that a small amount of records in this fonds were created prior to the creation of ESSDVP by Bank staff within the Environmentally Sustainable Development Vice Presidency (ESD); the records were brought into ESSDVP's recordkeeping system as a result of staff transfer into ESSDVP. The majority of the records in this fonds are clearly associated with the activities of Ian Johnson, ESSD Vice President from 1998 to 2006.
Records were transferred directly from sector units to the Archives using approved records retention and disposition schedules.
Accruals are expected.
* See Records of the Environment Sector ([WB IBRD/IDA ENV](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-environment-sector)).
* See Records of the Agriculture and Rural Development Sector ([WB IBRD/IDA AGR](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-agriculture-and-rural-development-sector)).
* See Records of the Social Development Sector ([WB IBRD/IDA 87 WB_IBRD/IDA_87](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-social-development-sector)).
* See Records of the Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research ([WB IBRD/IDA CGIAR](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-consultative-group-on-international-agricultural-research-cgiar)).
* See Records of the Environmentally Sustainable Development Vice Presidency ([WB IBRD/IDA 90 WB_IBRD/IDA_90](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-environmentally-sustainable-development-vice-presidency)).
* For records of ESSD Vice President Ian Johnson (1998-2006), see Records of Individual staff members -- Ian Johnson files ([WB IBRD/IDA STAFF-13](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/ian-johnson-files)).
Records are subject to the World Bank Policy on Access to Information.
- Budget and resource allocation, 1994 - 2000; WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_92-01; 0.60 linear feet of textual records
  Published
  Series consists of records related to, or the product of, budgetary planning and resource allocation. Included are a number of budget reports, including some that were created for the Environmentally Sustainable Development Vice Presidency (ESD). These include: ESD Work Program Indicators (FY96 and FY97); ESD Retrospective Reviews (FY 94, FY 95, and FY 96); ESD Original FY95 Work Program; ESD FY96-98 Business Plan; ESSD FY98-00 Business Plan; ESSD Final Budget Outcome. Also included are records that relateto: the Leadership Asset Management Program (LAMP); the allocation of funds to the Development Grant Facility (DGF); and budget planning for FY00 and FY01.
  The original order of the records has been maintained. Records are arranged in chronological order.
  Accruals are expected.
  Records are subject to the World Bank Policy on Access to Information.
  - Budget, Work Program, and Accounting Records - Environmentally Sustainable Development [ESD] Original Fiscal Year [FY] 1995 Work Program - Report - September 1994, 1994-09-01; 01833713
  - Budget, Work Program, and Accounting Records - Environmentally Sustainable Development [ESD] Work Program Indicators - Fiscal Year [FY] 1996 - 1997, 1995-09-01 - 1996-09-01; 01833711
  - Budget, Work Program, and Accounting Records - Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Development Network [ESSD] Business Plans - Reports, 1995-03-01 - 1997-04-01; 01833722
  - Budget, Work Program, and Accounting Records - Environmentally Sustainable Development [ESD] Retrospective Reviews - Reports, 1994-08-01 - 1996-07-01; 01833712
  - Budget, Work Program, and Accounting Records - FY99 Final Budget Outcome - Budget File, 1999-01-01 - 1999-12-31; 01832714
  - Budget, Work Program, and Accounting Records - Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Development Network [ESSD] Leadership Asset Management Program - General Correspondence - 2000, 2000-01-31 - 2000-10-12; 01833714
  - Budget, Work Program, and Accounting Records - Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Development Network [ESSD] and the Development Grant Facility - General Correspondence, 2000-11-06 - 2000-11-07; 01833731
  - Shared Unit Files - Policy Development Records - FY 02 - MC / VP Quarterly Business Review Meetings - Report, 2002-01-01 - 2002-12-31; 01832819
  - Shared Unit Files - Policy Development Records - ESSD FY 2001 Quarterly Business Review - Report, 2001-01-01 - 2001-12-31; 01832812
  - Budget, Work Program, and Accounting Records - ESSD Front Office Budget - Budget File, 1999-01-01 - 2000-12-31; 01832711
- CGIAR meeting and planning records, 1999 - 2002; WB IBRD/IDA WB_IBRD/IDA_92-02; 0.83 linear feet of textual records
  Series consists of records related to Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) and ESSD Vice President Ian Johnson's role as CGIAR Chairman. Johnson served as Chairman from 2000-2006. Records relate to CGIAR planning and policy development and to CGIAR meetings, conferences, and workshops.
  Series contains agendas, supporting materials, and notes related to a variety of meetings, conferences, and workshops participated in and/or attended by Ian Johnson, including: European Donors Meeting, Paris (17 April 2001); CGIAR System Office Workshop (13-14 March 2002); CGIAR North American Donors Meeting (5 April 2001); and CGIAR's Synthesis Meeting, Reading, UK (4-7 October 2000). Materials supporting the European Donors Meeting are also included.
  Supporting materials include numerous reports. A number of these reports relate to CGIAR planning, organizational changes and strategies and were authored by the CGIAR's Change Design and Management Team (CDMT). Reports on these activities preparedby the CGIAR Technical Advisory Committee (TAC) are also included.
  A small amount of records which relate to the Operation Evaluation Department's (OED) meta-evaluation of CGIAR of 2002 are also included. The majority of these records are correspondence and discuss CGIAR staff feedback and comments.
  * See Records of the Consultative Group on International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) ([WB IBRD/IDA CGIAR](https://archivesholdings.worldbank.org/records-of-consultative-group-on-international-agricultural-research-cgiar)).
  - Shared Unit Files - Policy Development Records - Critical Ecosystem Partnership Fund: Consultative Group for International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) - Correspondence File, 2001-01-01 - 2001-12-31; 01831237
  - Conferences and Seminars - Consultative Group On International Agricultural Research [CGIAR] System Office Workshop - March 13 - 14, 2002 - Workshop File, 2002-01-01 - 2002-03-14; 01833739
  - Operations Evaluation Department [OED] Meta Evaluation of the Consultative Group On International Agricultural Research [CGIR] - Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Development Network [ESSD] and CGIAR Secretariat Response - August 2002, 2002-07-30 - 2002-08-08; 01833738
  - Conferences and Seminars - Consultative Group On International Agricultural Research [CGIAR] New Vision and Strategy - Reading, United Kingdom - October 4 - 7, 2000 - Conference File, 1999-05-07 - 2000-10-30; 01833737
  - Conferences and Seminars - Consultative Group On International Agricultural Research [CGIAR] European Donors Meeting - Paris - April 17, 2001 - Conference File, 2001-04-11 - 2001-04-16; 01833745
  - Conferences and Seminars - Consultative Group On International Agricultural Research [CGIAR] North American Donors Meeting - New York - April 5, 2001 - Conference File, 2001-03-13 - 2001-04-05; 01833744
  - Conferences and Seminars - Ian Johnson and Robert Thompson Visit Centro Internacional de Mejoramiento de Maiz y Trigo [CIMMYT] - Conference File, 2000-07-07 - 2000-07-17; 01833746
  - Shared Unit Files - Policy Development Records - Critical Ecosystem Partnership Fund: Consultative Group for International Agricultural Research (CGIAR) - Correspondence File, 2000-01-01 - 2000-12-31; 01831236
- Trust Fund management and oversight, 1996 - 2003; WB IBRD/IDA 92 WB_IBRD/IDA_92-06; 2.01 linear feet of textual records
  Series consists of records related to ESSD's role in providing management, oversight, and resource allocation for those trust funds that involve ESSD sectors. Records relating to trust funds provided by Denmark (TF024153), Norway (TF0231295), and Italy (TF023333) are the most numerous. Records related to Denmark are dated from 1996-1997 and 2000 and include: proposals; trust fund agreements; budget requests; initiating briefs; and correspondence between ESD and Danish government ministers. Records from 2000 relate to a proposal for a possible second phase of the Danish ESSD Trust Fund. These records include a proposal by SDV to the Government of Denmark as well as debriefing and consultation notes and a copy of Denmark's Development Policy (2000). Records related to Italy include correspondence between Bank officials (including the Bank President and ESSD Vice President) and Italian officials including their American Ambassador. Also included is background material on the Trust Fund for Culture and Sustainable Development for which Italy provided funding. Records related to Norway include funding proposals by SDV as well as other Bank units external to ESSD. Also included are records relating to the Norwegian Trust Fund for Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Development (NTF-ESSD). These records include: status reports; reports; meetings notes; and background information on the Bank-Netherlands Partnership Program related to Water Resources Management. A small amount of correspondence from 1999 related to a proposed Social Development Trust Fund funded by Japan is also included.
  Records relating to funds managed or overseen by ESSDVP are also included. Records related to the launch and subsequent Donor Councils of the Critical Ecosystem Partnership Fund are included; correspondence related to this Fund is also included. In addition, the series also contains correspondence files for the Prototype Carbon Fund.
  A variety of records related to the general management of ESSD-related trust funds is also included. These include: records related to fund allocation and transfer; a list of task managers and division chiefs for specific, ESSD-related trust fund projects; and notes, slides and announcement emails for a Trust Fund Awareness Training program organized by the ESSDVP.
  - Records Related to Trust Fund Programs - Consultation on Netherlands Trust Fund - April 28, 2000, 2000-04-18 - 2000-04-21; 01833710
  - Records Related to Trust Fund Programs - Trust Fund Awareness Training - Presentation by Ian Johnson, 2001-12-12; 01833636
  - Records Related to Trust Fund Programs - Request for Exception to the Application of the Disbursement and Trust Fund Policies to Get Supported Conservation Funds - March 15, 2002, 2002-03-15 - 2002-04-15; 01833637
  - Records of the Trust Fund Cycle - Danish Trust Fund TF 024153 - Trust Fund File, 1996-04-18 - 1996-07-11; 01833621
  - Records Related to Trust Fund Programs - Consultations on Danish Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Development Network [ESSD] Trust Fund - November 2000 and June 2001, 1999-09-12 - 2001-06-14; 01833638
  - Records of the Trust Fund Cycle - Danish Trust Fund Extras - Trust Fund File - 1996 - 1997, 1996-04-08 - 1997-06-13; 01833625
  - Shared Unit Files - Policy Development Records - Critical Ecosystem Partnership Fund - Second Meeting of the Donor Council - Washington, D.C. - December 11, 2001, 2001-12-11; 01831198
  - Shared Unit Files - Policy Development Records - Critical Ecosystems Partnership Fund - Launch Design and DGF Application Form - Correspondence File, 2000-01-01 - 2000-12-31; 01831155
  - Shared Unit Files - Policy Development Records - Critical Ecosystems Partnership Fund - Report, 2000-01-01 - 2000-12-31; 01831154
  - Shared Unit Files - Policy Development Records - Critical Ecosystem Partnership Fund - First Meeting of the Donor Council - Meeting File - December 14, 2000, 2000-12-14; 01831197
  - Shared Unit Files - Policy Development Records - Prototype Carbon Fund - Correspondence File, 2001-01-01 - 2001-12-31; 01831153
  - Shared Unit Files - Policy Development Records - Prototype Carbon Fund - Correspondence File, 2000-01-01 - 2000-12-31; 01831152
  - Shared Unit Files - Policy Development Records - Prototype Carbon Fund - Correspondence File, 1998-01-01 - 1998-12-31; 01831150
  - Shared Unit Files - Policy Development Records - Fourth Meeting of the Donor Council - February 12, 2003 - Briefing Material for J. D. Wolfensohn, 2003-02-12; 01831200
  - Shared Unit Files - Policy Development Records - Critical Ecosystem Partnership Fund - Correspondence File, 1999-01-01 - 2001-12-31; 01831199
  - Shared Unit Files - Policy Development Records - Biocarbon Fund Memorandum of Understanding Meeting - February 24 - 26, 2003 - Correspondence File, 2003-02-24 - 2003-02-26; 01831239
  - Records of the Trust Fund Cycle - Danish Trust Fund TF 024153 - Trust Fund File, 1996-08-06 - 1997-08-29; 01833622
  - Shared Unit Files - Policy Development Records - Prototype Carbon Fund - Correspondence File, 1999-01-01 - 1999-12-31; 01831151
  - Records of the Trust Fund Cycle - Italian Trust Fund for Culture and Sustainable Development - Correspondence File - June - December 1999, 1999-03-29 - 1999-12-10; 01833627
  - Records of the Trust Fund Cycle - Trust Fund Representation Letters - Correspondence File - June - July 1997, 1997-06-27 - 1997-07-31; 01833628
  - Records of the Trust Fund Cycle - Norwegian Trust Fund for Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Development - Correspondence File - November 2001, 2001-10-31 - 2001-11-13; 01833635
  - Records Related to Trust Fund Programs - Norwegian Trust Fund for Environmentally and Socially Sustainable Development Network [ESSD] - 2000 - 2001, 1999-12-07 - 2000-09-18; 30181562
  - Records of the Trust Fund Cycle - Japan Integrated Social Development Trust Fund Proposal - Correspondence File - October 1999, 1999-10-28 - 2000-02-09; 01833630
- Management and oversight, 1998 - 2003; WB IBRD/IDA 92 WB_IBRD/IDA_92-07; 5.22 linear feet of textual records
  Series consists of records related to management and oversight activities of ESSDVP. Records primarily relate to high-level meetings attended by ESSD Vice President Ian Johnson within ESSD as well as other units and committees of the World Bank. This includes meetings with Bank President Wolfensohn and Managing Director Shengman Zhang as well as meetings of the Bank's Operational Vice Presidents. Records from Bank-wide Corporate Days (1998-2002) and Strategic Forums (2000-2001) are also included. These records include: background notes (prepared for ESSDVP Ian Johnson by ESSD staff); presentation notes and slides; correspondence; progress reports; agendas; and follow-up materials.
  Records related to management and organizational meetings of the ESSD include: ESSD Council meetings (2001-2003); ESSD Anchor meetings (2000-2001, 2003); ESSD FY02-04 Business Planning MD/VP Meeting; ESSD FY04-06 Strategic Planning; ESSD Knowledge Management strategy (1998-2000); and ESSD Management Retreats (including EnvironmentSector Board retreat [2002]) and Team Meetings.
  - Committee Records - DGF Applications to be Discussed at the Environmnetally and Socially Sustainable Develoment [ESSD] Council Meeting - February 26, 2002 - Reports, 2002-02-26; 01832596
  - Committee Records - ESSD Anchor Meetings - Correspondence File, 2000-02-08 - 2001-05-17; 01832681
  - ESSD Anchor Meeting - Background Documentation - February 26, 2003, 2003-02-25 - 2003-02-26; 01832682
  - Environment Sector Board Retreat - November 19, 2002 - Background Documentation, 2002-11-14 - 2002-11-19; 01832696
  - Organization and Management Records - ESSD FY 02-04 Business Planning Meeting - Background Documentation, 2001-03-20; 01832730
  - Organization and Management Records - ESSD Strategic Planning Management Meeting - Background Documentation - FY 2004-2006, 2002-11-26; 01832733
  - Organization and Management Records - Knowledge Management in ESSD - Background Documentation, 1999-01-01 - 2000-12-31; 01832805
  - Organization and Management Records - Knowledge Management in ESSD - Correspondence File, 1998-01-01 - 1998-12-31; 01832807
  - Organization and Management Records - FY2003 ESSD - Wide Learning Program - Plan for Strategic Learning Centers - Background Documentation, 2002-07-16; 01832809
  - Shared Unit Files - Policy Development Records - ESSD Staffing and Human Resources - Correspondence File, 1998-01-01 - 1998-12-31; 01832811
  - Shared Unit Files - Policy Development Records - Office of Business Ethics and Integrity Investigation of Alleged Conflict of Interest - International Task Force on Commodity Risk Management - Correspondence File, 2001-10-01 - 2001-12-31; 01832815
  - Shared Unit Files - Policy Development Records - ESSD Staff Survey - Correspondence File, 1999-07-01 - 1999-07-31; 01832821
  - Briefing Books for Senior Officials - Commodity Risk Management - Briefing for Shengman Zhang - Briefing Papers - July 10, 2001, 2001-06-01 - 2002-07-10; 01833130
  - Briefing Books for Senior Officials - Quarterly Reports to Shengman Zhang on Rural Development and on Safeguard Activities - January 2003 - Briefing Notes, 2003-01-17 - 2003-01-28; 01833141
  - Briefing Books for Senior Officials - Human Development Report 2002 - Presentation and Meeting with Sakiko Fakuda Parr, United Nations Development Programme [UNDP] - Briefing Notes, 2002-01-01 - 2003-01-14; 01833150
  - Briefing Books for Senior Officials - Community Driven Development - Briefing with Shengman Zhang - Briefing Notes - March 1, 2002, 2002-02-25 - 2002-03-01; 01833389
  - Briefing Books for Senior Officials - Commodity Risk Management - Technical Briefing - Board Meeting - Briefing Notes - December 14, 2001, 2001-12-03 - 2001-12-10; 01833390
  - Briefing Books for Senior Officials - Ian Johnson Meeting with J. D. Wolfensohn - Briefing Notes - June 6, 2001, 2001-05-21 - 2001-06-06; 01833396
  - Organization and Management Records - Ian Johnson Meetings with World Bank Managing Director Shengman Zhang - General Correspondence - 1999, 1999-09-02 - 1999-10-12; 01833397
  - Mining CEO Initiative - J.D. Wolfensohn Meeting with Rio Tinto, Noranda and Phelps Dodge - October 28, 1999 - Background Documentation, 1999-10-27 - 1999-10-28; 01833419
  - Aga Khan - Development Network - Visit to the World Bank - October 13 - 15, 1999 - Background Documentation, 1999-10-13 - 1999-10-15; 01833420
  - Eastern African Biodiversity Trust - Ian Johnson with Hal Wackman and Richard Leakey - April 24, 2002 - Background Documentation, 2001-07-11 - 2002-04-19; 01833422
  - Eastern African Biodiversity Fund - Draft Concept for Discussion - April 24, 2002, 2002-04-24; 01833428
  - Partnership to cut Hunger and Poverty in Africa - Meeting with United States under Secretary of State, Alan Larson - March 6, 2002 - Background Documentation, 2001-11-01 - 2002-03-04; 01833434
  - Ian Johnson Meeting with French Development Agency Executive Director, Pierre Jacquet - September 25, 2002 - Background Documentation, 2002-09-06 - 2002-09-25; 01833438